Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
I bow in respect before Lady Sourire.
What are you carrying, Mr Jiang?
His majesty has specially bestowed this to you.
Look, my Lady!
The jade that makes the sole is the famous variety of Lantian jade, which feels gentle and will never make your feet feel cold.
The inside of the shoe is hollow and contains various spices. His majesty said it called "Distribute fragrance step by step".
The tips of the shoes are adorned by Hepu pearls, which are not as noble as the East pearls, but perfectly round, huge and gorgeous.
The most special is the upper, which is made of Shu brocade with gold engraving.
The Shu brocade is very difficult to get, especially the gold engraving one.
I have heard that it takes ten people three months to make a bolt, so the brocade is very valuable.
Such beautiful cloth is usually hard to see , let alone be made of the upper of the shoes.
I am grateful to His Majesty.
But I'm a little curious about where the Shu brocade came from
I remember that the tributary Shu brocade had just came in February, and was only given the Express and the Empress Dowager.
The new tributes are supposed to arrive in February
This shows your majesty's special favor for you, My Lady.
Shu brocade bureau had new design and sent only one bolt here from far away.
Only one bolt, His Majesty ordered the Household Department to make the shoes for you.
His Majesty is coming.
"Speak of angels and you will hear their wings"
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Please put on these shoes and let me see.
Look good?
These shoes fit you perfectly, it seems that I am right.
What?
I asked the bureau of needlework to make shoes to your size and the shoes really fit you.
But I've never told Your Majesty the size of my feet.
How could I sleep with you for so many days and not know the size of your feet.
I specially asked the bureau of embroidery embroidered mandarin duck（This bird symbolizes husband and wife）
Your Majesty...
Huan Huan, did I make you unhappy?
You seem to have something weighing on your heart since we came back from the Summer Palace.
No, Your Majesty didn't make me unhappy.
It's just that your majesty is so kind to me that I'm a little worried.
Don't worry. I'll give you whatever I promise. I'll protect you
I know Your Majesty's fondness for me.
But previously Your Majesty's fondness for Consort Fleur and Mei Zhuang was as much as mine.
I am afraid that Your Majesty are just fond of me.
The fondness is love.
What if it's just fondness instead of true love?
Maybe Your Majesty will make an exception for me.
As long as there's a little true love in the fondness, I will be happy.
Don't be silly.
"When we shall be able to trim wicks again, together in your western window, I would talk to you about this moment of night rain in Sichuan."
Your Majesty and I trim the wick together, but there is no rain outside the window to talk about.
It is in clear weather here, but Yunlin's letter said that it rains a lot in Sichuan.
Fortunately, the scene of night rain in Sichuan where he stayed was very beautiful, so it also could ease the tiredness of the journey.
Take a look at this.
It was delivered here in no time indeed.
It is for they "galloped through the dust for a Consort's smile".
Unfortunately, this is not my most favored color.
Living life is not unlike making clothes,
for it must be filled with color and excitement.
Your Highness usually prefers vibrant colors,
however, these colors are not so bad.
Since they are not usually available at this time,
it was probably not easy to acquire these two rolls of Shu Brocade (silk fabric).
Truth be told, a lot of thought were put into this gift.
Look Your Highness.
These flower decorations are made using moon white threads intertwined with silver threads.
These would shine brightly under the sunlight.
I appreciate their thoughts.
It's good that they recognize,
it doesn't no matter how valuable something is,
I will get my hands on it if I desire.
Yes.
Unlike some others.
Even if given Shu Brocade shoes.
It will still be "wears a royal garment yet not a true prince".
Have the Embroidery Department make clothes using these fabric.
Everything seems fine...
But how come I don't recognize these patterns.
Yes.
Usually they're patterns of peony and phoenix.
This is rather interesting.
Take a look and see if you can tell what flower this is.
My Lady, this is Morning Glory, also known as The Face of Eventide.
How tacky.
This flower blooms at dawn and withers come dusk. It only blooms once.
It fades before the sunrise.
Shut up.
Do not utter such inauspicious words.
Bastards.
The Department of Textiles must have lost their minds.
Tricking me and giving me bad luck with these flowers.
Song Zhi
Yes
Tear these up and send them back to the Department of Textiles.
Your Highness, this flower is not common,
no wonder they made a mistake.
If these silk were destroyed there would be a lot of gossip.
Since most people don't know this flower.
Your Highness can just feign ignorance and give these away as gifts.
Gift them to her.
Who?
She has shoes made of the same thing,
now paired together with these clothes,
she can show her true light as His Highness' favorite.
You are finally back.
Both you and An LingRong went to the Summer Palace
I was the only one left.
I was so bored.
What about your madam?
My madam scolds me constantly.
She complains that I talk too much.
She tells me I should simmer down.
"I can be favored by His Highness just like Lady An if I be more obedient".
You should listen to her, she is trying to coach you.
She also said.
I have yet to talk with His Highness even though it has been one yer since I arrived.
That I am never peaceful.
If I meet His Majesty, I will have to obey even more rules.
I'd rather not.
Tell that to His Highness when you see him.
My Lady, Mr. Zhou from the Palace of Earthly Honor is here.
Greetings, Lady Sourire.
Rise.
Thank you.
Consort Fleur received two rolls of Shu Brocade.
The colors are fresh and attractive,
so she ordered two garments for you.
Many thanks to Her Highness.
JinXi. Take them.
My Lady.
This silk garment is elegant and beautiful,
made with exquisite craftsmanship.
However, the Priest from the Baohua Hall mentioned last time.
Your Lady shouldn't to be associated with the "mouse" this year. (Mouse is pronounced "Shu")
Different word but the same sound is also bad omen.
If these were shoes used for walking then it wouldn't have been so bad.
But as for clothes,
maybe it's best for My Lady to wear them next year.
If I'm understanding JinXi correctly,
Lady Sourire cannot wear the clothes made by Her Highness?
Indeed, You Lady is the now apple of His Majesty's eye.
Having His Majesty's precious award and favor, treasure from H er Highness is only dust to You Lady.
Her Highness always comme nts that
a person of integrity should have no fear to evil spirits .
Although the priests' suggestion are credible,
Her Highness' fortune and blessings
would definitely protect You Lady from evil as well.
Jinxi's words comes from her good intent.
Mister'd better not misunderstand her.
Please report my appointment to Her Highness that later I would thank Her Highness in person.
Then I beg you my leave.
Come here. Let me look at it.
This dress is very lovely!
You are given such a beautiful dress, but Huan'er you doesn't look happy.
What kind is this flower of?
I have never seen the flower before.
This is Xiyan (the flowers withering at dusk),
the morning glory.
The morning glory? Does the flower have a connotation?
Indeed the flower is lovely,
but the intention behind this unexpected present
is too indistinct to recognize.
You are not alone on this suspicion.
Any unexpected thing must happen for an arranged plan.
Huan'er, this dress is the suitable match
with your shoes made of Shu Brocade (silk made in ancient Sichuan).
Dressing up with them, Huan'er you would be the most prominent one
among all the concubines,
in this October's Chrysanthemum Celebration.
Settle them in the wardrobe.
I pay my respect to Your Majesty.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesty.
You may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Sit down.
Is anything wrong with you?
I am more than obliged to stay with Your Majesty, in good or bad times.
His Majesty is busy with government affairs.
I should take his place to be a good companion for Your Majesty.
Your concern is sweet.
The night in autumn is getting cold.
Has Your Majesty's cough alleviated?
Yes, it has.
I remember Your Majesty are used to warm conditions,
so I asked them to make this cloak of fox fur for Your Majesty.
Is this ink fox's fur (fox with black fur)?
Yes, it is.
My brother now takes his office in Qinghai.
He got two ink foxes in hunting by chance.
I think only Your Majesty can bring out the sedate side of the fur of ink fox,
while I am too young and inexperienced.
I know Your Majesty has a deep belief in Buddhism.
I choose the brocade which has the passionflower on it for the lining
It is my humble wish that Your Majesty would agree on my thoughts on this cloak.
I am greatly warmed by you.
Bamboo, take it.
Yes.
Why do you dress so plainly?
Although I am young and inexperienced in front of Your Majesty,
I 'd better dress up myself less bight or vividly
among concubines who are much younger than me.
Not to mention dressing up myself full of charm,
like Noble Lady Sourire and Attendant An.
Noble Lady Sourire is always mentioned to me,
my only impression on her
is that she has a sweet appearance.
It is sorry if Your Majesty hasn't seen her recently.
His Majesty gave a pair of shoes to her, which is made of Shu Brocade.
Even the shoe sole is made from blue jade.
Noble Lady Sourire also made two dresses from Shu Brocade,
which match properly with her shoes and add to her charm.
Oh yes?
But according to my memory,
the Shu Brocade is not available at this time.
Noble Lady Sourire is full of charm.
How would His Majesty say no to any of her requests?
The only suspense is
how much the Shu Brocade has cost.
She is new to the palace.
The Emperor treats her as a child.
Farrah
Is the Noble Lady Sourire conscientious ?
That is hard to say.
If I say she is,
Your Majesty will blame her for not being considerate as today I desired for cool and did wear less
and me for being partial for her.
If I say she is not, she is truly a thoughtful person.
But I haven't seen her for three or four days since I have been busy with state affairs recently.
Your Majesty still denied your partiality.
That is really a partiality for her.
Auntie please don't laugh at me.
Though you are occupied with state affairs,
Your Majesty only have not seen her for three or four days.
But how often do you see Consort Fleur,
the Empress,
Concubine Estime and so forth ?
It's alright not to frequent the imperial harem if Your Majesty is busy.
However, you will sadden the imperial concubines if you show closeness and distantness.
Your Majesty taught a good lesson.
I remembered.
The ink fox fur of such high quality,
seems from the QingHai Region.
Your Majesty really have bright eyes and a clear mind,
for you are able to see it's a ink fox fur in such a dim palace.
Then you are abler to see the harem and state affairs as clearly as a blazing fire.
This ink fox overcoat is made of fox skin from ink fox.
The Consort Fleur specially chose satin with passionflower pattern as lining,
appropriate inside and outside, bringing out the best in each other.
I clearly understood what Your Majesty said.
Today I heard that Your Majesty awarded a dangling ornament to Consort Fleur.
I am going to see and admire it as it will appear more lustrous in the candlelight.
Grace and mercy can not only be used in the imperial court
but also in the harem.
Currently there are some remaining issues in the Northwest region.
However, the tribal headmen in the Southwest are still dangers from within,
for which great effort is needed to pacify.
Nian Gengyao is capable and loyal.
Your Majesty should put him in an important position unless he becomes arrogant and imperious.
It is a major contribution to suppress the West Region.
Nian Gengyao will arrive in the imperial palace and present himself before me in October.
I will definitely praise and reward him.
Consort Fleur's pleasancy run out.
The pleasancy has to be made through a long process, thus not easy to obtain.
Is Your Majesty not going to reward her?
Of course I will reward her as she has been using it for so many years
Your Highness
Has my brother returned?
The general returned and paid tribute after he suppressed the West Region,
but the general will present himself before His Majesty first.
His Majesty has always been kind to the General.
There must be important conversation between them at the moment.
Sure.
But it's lunch time.
They need to have lunch though they have important affairs to discuss.
Your Highness
His Majesty asked your Highness to have lunch in the Hall of Mental Cultivation
Please wait outside.
I will be there in a minute.
Though there are a variety of dishes in the palace,
I’m not sure if they suit your taste.
Just try with your preference.
If they are really unpalatable,
I’ll order some dishes else for you from Consort Fleur’s kitchen.
I really can’t bother Your Majesty with such a trifle.
What a grace to have this opportunity
having lunch with Your Majesty and Consort Fleur.
Sit down.
We are having lunch as a family.
Frequent standing up, gratitude and apology will spoil this meal.
Have your seat.
Thank Your Majesty and Consort Fleur.
This grilled lamb is fresh and tender,
which I fascinate a lot. Have a taste.
Exactly delicious. Thank you Your Majesty.
Brother,
on a granted meal with His Majesty,
you are supposed to be serve by servants instead of by yourself.
Your Majesty, I’m sorry for my brashness.
As you have been on an expedition of war for a long time,
must be accustomed to attend to everything personally. It’s fine.
I should obey the rules in the palace.
Just act as your will.
Rules are made for courtesy among the Emperor and ministers,
not for constraint among family members.
So it is.
This braised duck and cubilose in front of me seems good.
Please do me a favor, Mr. Su.
General-in-Chief, please enjoy it.
You smashed up blo bzang bstan 'dzin’s military
in one fist within only fifteen days.
And gradually cleaned up the remnants of shattered army
during the past eight months.
You pacified and overawed the North-West for me.
You’re really my benefactor.
I’m not qualified yet for Your Majesty’s compliment.
Since I ascended the throne not too long ago,
the court and the commonalty are still not stable enough.
The lords are waiting in the wings.
If the border is in chaos,
I’ll be between hammer and anvil, lacking consideration for the whole.
The great contribution you made
not only worth my praise,
but also deserves an everlasting gratitude
from the hearts of my descendants and people.
One cannot be my descendant with an unfaithful heart,
neither can be my subject if with disloyalty.
While Consort Fleur pours her heart in the harem,
I am faithfully serving the country on the boundary.
We brother and sister
will both exert the utmost effort with elaborateness.
Consort Fleur has served me with cautious and consideration for years
And you’ve been fight for me as my loyalest subordinate
It’s a fortune to have you by my side
If there’s ten more ministers like you
I will not be worrying about governing the country anymore
With all my grace, Your Majesty
This cup of drink is for you two
I am grateful to Your Majesty
Yes
Does Yunnan-Guizhou and Gansu-Shanxi still peaceful
Everything is just fine
before entering the capita
I’ve heard that the tribe Xieersu which located near the Mount Zhuozi wasn’t so stable
That may occurred some rebellion
Indeed that I’ve got messages that
An insurgency was fought at Zhuanglang, Gansu province
It’s simple to put down a rebellion which is launched by mob
Wisely are you, Your Majesty
We ought to be cautious that
the Tribe Xieerdan had conspired with the Tribe Geerdan in Xinkiang
Then what’s your opinion
Xieersu is only a small tribe
It seems too excessive to send a valiant general
Yet too thoughtless not to deal with it instantly
Thus I make bold to recommend my second son NianFu to put down the rebellion
Though young but experienced
I would like to give him a try
Your Majesty, I can’t interfere in the politics
I shouldn’t be here
listening to the conversation between you and brother
The fair I talk to your brother is not only about politics
But also about our family
It doesn’t matter
Consort Fleur is right
It a precious chance to dining with Your Majesty
It isn't appropriate to speak of tha at family reunion
Good
We shall all focus on the course
The weather is getting cold
since the fifteenth of October every meal will add a pot
though it’s fourteenth today
your majesty still command the the Imperial Kitchen
to prepare the assorted pot of you
you have to be graceful to our king’s mercy through every meal you eat
I am grateful to Your Majesty
Pots warm the body
You and I are of one mind
I felt warmer in the heart
Yes, your majesty
Have a taste
Yes, Your Majesty
I bid Your Highness Consort Fleur goodbye.
I bid Your Highness General Nian goodbye.
My brother
This meal almost made my heart in my boots
What’s going on with you
The emperor said that the grilled lamb was his favorite
How could you taste it before the emperor did
Besides you command Supeisheng to serve for you
Who is Suoeisheng
He is the servant that has served the emperor for decades
Since he was young
How dare you can command him
You know my temper.
I hate those feculent eunuchs.
But it is the boundary of the palace.
I cannot overstep.
I definitely want a best eunuch to serve for me.
To be impolite,
After hard battles and notable merits,
can't I deserve the best eunuch to serve for me?
As the eunuch of His Majesty, he also serves for me.
In that case, he might as well serve for you once.
But never do it again.
The trifling poet Li Bai can take off the boots of Gao Lishi
by virtue of his scanty literature talent.
It's Su Peisheng's fortune to serve for me.
Besides, there are something His Majesty can do but you can't.
There are something His Majesty can say but you can't.
For His Majesty, to say that we are family is a polite greeting.
For you, such words are to overstep your bounds
You didn't drink. Why were you drunken?
The longer you stay in the palace,
the smaller your mind becomes
I just follow His Majesty's words.
Let alone it goes without saying His Majesty and us are family.
You are his beloved Consort.
I am his brother-in-law.
Aren't we kin blood?
Thank AmitÄbha Bud3dha. Fortunately His Majesty didn't blame you.
His Majesty shouldn't be angry
if he asked you to send me to my palace
and then go back again.
What's wrong with you?
Were you bullied by the Empress?
The Empress isn' capable to do that.
Instead, the newcome Lady Sourire,
shows off her gift of gab.
She fomented dissension, counting against me.
Just because of her,
His Majesty deprived me of autority in palace management
and didn't reinstate me until now
How dare a trivial Lady give offence to her superiors
She is in favor.
I can do nothing.
I heard that her father was a Minister as well.
Oh? What's his name?
Zhen Yuandao.
Good
His daughter counted against you.
Thus, I counted against him.
Fortunately I have my brother shield me.
Otherwise, my grievance is coutless.
Don't be afraid. You have me.
Your Majesty, General Nian is back.
Your Majesty.
Take your seat.
I'm honored to obey.
General Nian, please have a cup of tea.
Your Majesty.
Last time I denounced the grand coordinator of Zhi Li
Zhao Zhiyuan [the name of the coordinator]
He has great foppery，
far from shouldering the responsibility.
I wonder the decision from the perspective of His Majesty.
Now that you think he is not qualified.
Then I will deprive his authority.
That is very wise, Your Majesty.
You and I are monach and subject outside,
relatives inside.
If I cannot become an extrodinary emperor,
your honesty and sincerity to me cannot be awarded.
(Yes, Your Majesty..)
If you cannot become an extrodinary General,
my apprecaition cannot be reciprocated
We had better become eternal examples for our offsprings.
I will devote(risk?) my life to reciprocate the imperial favor.
Just sit down.
I am tired to hear
your appreciation on every occasion.
Yes, Your Majesty.
For your commitment and contribution, I reward you……
You must be tired today.
Return to your house and rest now.
Come to me another day.
I humbly thank Your Majesty
Your Highness, Xiao-Xiazi heard that His Majesty obliged to General Nian.
Your Highness.
Autumn, why it is getting cold here?
Because the wind rises.
Would you like to add a coat?
A coat will do me no good.
These days, His Majesty only visits Consort Fleur.
He didn’t even bother stepping into the Palace of Great Benevolence.
The Palace of Great Benevolence has always been desolate.
It gets warm only when His Majesty comes.
But now it is even colder.
If this palace is obliged to Consort Fleur for General Nian’s contribution, it would be scorching ever since.
Your Majesty only stays with me these days but doesn’t favor others.
If you are generous, I’ll check Consort Astuce.
Your Majesty, I didn’t mean it.
It’s late at night.
You’d better not go.
I knew it that you want me to stay.
I always stayed with you when you just entered the palace.
Sometimes I would leave Yixiu alone, who just had just got her ladyship.
Before I entered the palace, you had a long time staying with Her Majesty.
Her Majesty entered the palace early.
It is only fair when you spare more time to stay with me.
Not that I don’t want to stay with you.
But I’m the emperor now.
I have to govern the state.
There are many concubines in the palace.
I can’t leave them alone because of you.
So do you think of others while staying with me?
Now you are talking like a child.
You were a secondary wife before, now a consort.
I need you to dedicatedly manage the things and people in the palace for me.
Right?
You need to bear with Her Majesty for her health condition.
Yes, I understand.
Sourire, you really have an aesthetic mood.
You’ve been studying how to make Lily Perfume for more than 7 days.
How come you are not tired?
I need to find things to do to kill time at long and lonely nights.
Hasn’t His Majesty visited you as well?
He hasn’t come again after having lunch with me six days ago.
It's about more than half a month.
But I can't complain it.
I heard from Consort Astuce that
she'd not seen the Emperor since she had came back to the palace.
The cold Autumn killed almost all the flowers,
only left Consort Fleur outshining.
She has her joyfulness,
while we also have our own.
You're not feeling well?
I got a cold this morning, and just a few days would heal it.
You don't have to worry.
Actually, the fabrication method of the multi-mixed spice has lost.
Even in the palace, it's seldom seen.
Everything is ready-made.
We can't get any fun from it.
Making it by ourselves is a good way to kill time.
Moreover, once the multi-mixed spice is made successfully,
It would be useful in winter days.
It combined with the stove,
you may feel you are surrounded by a sea of flowers.
Exactly, thanks to the spice business my father did
before he got an official position.
Thus he got lots of secrets recipes about spice fabrications.
I studied them for a few days at home.
Finally, I found that several ingredients may be available.
That's great. Then you dictate and I'll write it down.
Since Your Majesty like hearing Attendant An singing,
and it's been a long time not enjoying her songs.
Why not asking her to sing for us?
It would be a great pleasure for me to enjoy with Your Majesty.
It's already deep night. Don't bother to ask her to come.
Your Majesty...
But there's no problem only if you like.
Zhou Ninghai!
Yes, Your Highness.
Ask her to come.
Yes.
What in your mind is just written on this paper.
What's wrong?
Since you are such knowledgeable,
how did you write this wrong character?
Where's the radical of this character.
Your heart flies away with the Emperor,
even the radical follows by.
You are more and more glib-tongued.
I hope the Emperor can deliver a decree to take you away.
Then you'll be quite.
Who is glib-tongued?
It's just you are diffident.
Look at your work!
I bow in respect before Your Highness.
May your mistress peace.
What bothers Mr.Zhou to come?
The Emperor wants to hear Attendant An singing,
and he is waiting in the Palace of Earthly Honor.
The Emperor is with Consort Fleur now,
so it may be improper for me to come.
What about tomorrow?
The Emperor is waiting.
If you want to violate the decree,
you'd better do it yourself.
Please don't embarrass our servants.
Jinxi, go to get my zither.
My lady...
I'll go with Attendant An since the song is monotonous,
and play the zither to amuse the Emperor.
I think Consort Fleur won't mind me.
You are willing to play the zither.
then Her Highness would be pleased.
Please take us there.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesty and Your Highness.
All rise.
Thank Your Majesty.
Lady Sourire,
why are you here? It's too late and cold.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.